Guide to the Faculty Club Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Faculty Club records
1911-1979
RU 1063
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.5
The records consist of meeting minutes, correspondence, and other historical material documenting the activities of the Faculty Club.
Yale University. Faculty Club
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies, and organizations.
Information about Access
The collection is open for research
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Information About Creator(s)
The Yale Faculty Club was established in 1921. Located at 149 Elm Street in the former home of Rev. Anson Phelps Stokes, secretary of Yale from 1899 to 1921, the Club was administered by the University Entertainment Committee. Members were served tea, cake and sandwiches every afternoon, with suppers on Thursday evenings. In 1923, the Club took over its own administration. Over the years important developments in the facilities and activities of the Club resulted in increased membership. By 1936, membership in the Club had grown to 518 or 80% of those eligible. By 1956, the total reached 988. Interest groups for faculty women were organized for the first time in 1948. Although efforts were regularly made to recruit new members, decreased participation and use of the Faculty Club lead to its closure in 1977.
The Committee immediate set about the tremendous task of renovating and decorating. The Committee borrowed chairs, tables, rugs, and a little of everything from their friends, often catching those on their way to the Graduate Club to give a helping hand. Much of the Club's money went for coal, and two students were given lodging for taking care of the furnace and cleaning the side walks. Mr. and Mrs. F. Wallace Chatterton were secured as caretakers for the first year for a fee of $50 per month.
In December 1922, the faculty was invited to tea and the club house was opened. No meals were served the first season. When members of the club wanted to have lunch, tea, or dinner there, they brought their own food and dishes. There were no dues or officers. The following fall the house opened with Mrs. Paul White appointed as hostess and manager. She served in this capacity until the fall of 1930, living with her small daughter in the north wing of the Club. Her duties were to be hostess at all hours, make and serve tea every afternoon, and arrange all private parties.
The Committee supplemented its entertainment allowance with modest dues of one dollar per member to cover the expense of heating and operating costs. Tea was made on a hot plate in the pantry and, with cake and sandwiches, was served every afternoon for the price of ten cents. Weekly tea dances were held on Saturday afternoons from November to March. The charge was fifty cents per couple. Student orchestras provided the music. Thursday evening suppers were supplied by Mrs. Wilder Tileston and Mrs. Charles Tilden, the food being cooked in Mrs. Tileston's kitchen and brought to the Club in containers. In the winter of 1923 they served once a week for thirteen weeks, at a charge of fifty cents per person. Service was limited to fifty people. Reservations were supposedly closed at one o'clock on Wednesday.
In the spring of 1923, the Club took over its own administration, electing Dean Henry S. Graves president, Prof. Carl F. Shreiber, treasurer, and Mrs. Edward Noyes, secretary. The newly elected officers held their first meeting at the Faculty Club on June 1, 1923. During that year, the officers and some members of the University Entertainment Committee comprised the Executive Board of the Club, controlling all dealings with the Corporation and all financial matters. Social activities were still in the hands of the University Entertainment Committee.
The social life of the Club continued to grow. The kitchen was made usable and private dinners and luncheons were held. Lectures, Sunday musicals, and informal entertainment was arranged. Prof. Karl Young gave the first tea-time talk, speaking on educational problems. A kindergarten teacher was at the Club mornings to watch over faculty children.
For several years the Club operated on a modest budget and made due with its inadequate furnishings. In 1926, the university loaned the club $5000 for a new heating plant. In 1929, Francis P. Garvan, Class of 1897, gave the Club the money to restore and furnish the house adequately. Shortly thereafter, a scale of Club dues was established to meet increased needs.
Description of the Collection
The records consist of meeting minutes, correspondence, and other historical material documenting the activities of the Faculty Club.
College teachers -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Faculty -- Societies, etc.; Yale University. Faculty Club
- Faculty Club records, 1911-1979; Accession 19ND-A-477
  - Minutes
    - Vol. I (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. II (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vol. III (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Vol. IV (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Vol. IV (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Vol. V (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Vol. V (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Vol. VI (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Vol. VI (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Vol. VII (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Vol. VIII (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Vol. IX (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Documentary history
    - 1921-1924 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - 1924-1928 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 1928-1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1933-1941 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - 1941-1945 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - 1948-1951 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - 1960-1967 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Notebooks: programs, by-laws, minutes and reports
    - Vol I (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Vol I (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Vol II (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Vol II (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Vol III (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Vol III (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Vol IV (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Vol IV (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Vol V (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Vol VI (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Executive Board: minutes
    - 1960-1963 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - 1964-1970 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Faculty teas, 1911-1919 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Entertainment Committee, 1922-1923 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - History by Mr. George Nettleton; annual reports; membership lists; clippings, 1921-1979 (Box 7, Folder 39)
- Faculty Club records, circa 1940-1976; Accession 2008-A-093
  - History: Early years of the Faculty Club, circa 1938-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Application blanks, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ecklund-Cooper correspondence re department chairmen and deans, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles of Association and by-laws, 1942-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bicentennial, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles of Association and By-laws, letter of agreement with University, brief history of club, 1921-1964, 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - House committee and related subjects: casino night, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Re: taxes, liquor license: job description - tax and dues; Wiggins and Dana; Howard Parrish, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A proposal to the Women's Organization at Yale, 1966 November (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Club officers, governors, accessions, historian, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Anscombe - program, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Faculty Handbook; Yale Faculty Club Membership List, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Complaints on dues, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Graduate Club, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Nominating Committee, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memos to membership, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Osea Noss material re membership; cards, some old material, 1955-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notices: Board meetings, annual, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence: other, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - President's reports, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Former president's letters, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Printing, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Questionnaire, 1973 April (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Reciprocal agreements of other clubs; Faculty Club rules and regulations, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Special meeting of membership, 1976 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Treasurer's reports - money?, 1959-1976 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and by-laws - proposed and worked on; history of club, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Brochures, clippings, 1965-1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)